בוקר
טוב.
Boker tov. Okay, today's דף daf is ק"א, kof aleph, 101, and
we're in triple digits and we start with the משנה mishna on
the top. Okay, so here we go.
Afterwards, afterwards, let's get going on the דף. daf. We're already six
minutes in. הדלת שבמוקצה, Hadeles shebe-muktza, a door in a מוקצה, muktza,
which is, you know, what מוקצה muktza means, something that's set aside
and designated here, basically means a door of the building that opens
up into like a back alley, an underused door that opens up
into a back alley. And somehow bizarrely we are no longer talking
about עירובין Eruvin issues, we're not even talking about carrying issues.
You'd think we were back in מסכת שבת Masechet Shabbos where we're
talking about הלכות שבת Hilchos Shabbos issues and also some somewhat random
collection of הלכות שבת Hilchos Shabbos issues. I mean, you might have
remembered that we went from talking about drawing water from a well,
which was at least a question of a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid,
רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, to climbing on a tree, although it started
with the tree with overhanging branches, so it started with the רשות
היחיד, reshus hayachid, but then it became about climbing on a tree,
and now we're talking about issues about closing doors which are not
fully attached and to what degree that's considered to be בונה, boneh,
adding to the structure. Okay, so somebody can write a doctoral dissertation
on why the organization of this last פרק perek of עירובין. Eruvin.
But anyway, הדלת שבמוקצה, Hadeles shebe-muktza, you have this door that opens
up into this back alley, וחדקים שבפרצה, vechadakim shebepirtza, or similarly you
have types of like thorn like
bundles of thorns or sticks that you use to fill up a
hole in the wall,
מחצלאות, machatzalos, or similarly you've got like a mat that you use
to fill up a hole in the wall. I hope that there's,
you know, you don't need to have security of your house, but
okay. אין נועלים בהן, ein nolim bahen, you cannot lock them, meaning
use them to close the door on שבת, shabbos, אלא אם כן
גבוהים מן הארץ, ella im kein gevohin min ha'aretz, they have to
be, you know, higher than the ground. They cannot be dragging on
the ground because if basically you know they were not attached in
a way that they were that they were lifted off the ground,
then it is seen as if you're doing a construction. These are
doors that are not really that are not generally used and
and it's seen more like you're adding to the wall of the
building than actually just using a door.
It's a door that's already there?
Yeah, it is a door that's there, but if you take a
look, if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says the third
line of רש"י, Rashi, that because this is like a back door
to a back alley, he says אין בעל הבית חושש לעשות לו
דלת תלויה כראוי וקבועה אלא כפיפה כנגד הפתח. ein baal habayis choshesh
laasos lo deles teluya kera'uy ukevua ella kefefa keneged hapessach. Okay, so
רש"י Rashi says it's basically more like a big plank that you
use to fill up the hole than a door that's really attached
on hinges. Okay, so that's like adding to a construction of a
wall. So let's take a look at the גמרא. gemara. Thank you.
רמינהו, remini, I'll ask you on this. Thank you. דלת הנגררת, deles
hanigreret, if you have a door that drags, if you have a
door that's dragging, ומחצלת הנגררת, umachatzeles hanigreret, or a mat that's dragging,
so similar to the משנה, mishna, just maybe being a little bit
more clear what the problem is, that it's not fully suspended, it's
dragging, right? Because the משנה mishna demanded it be גבוה מן הארץ.
gevoha min ha'aretz. וקנקן הנגרר, vekankan hanigrar, קנקן kankan here does not
mean a like a bottle, but it means again some type of
an implement that is dragged that would be used to fill a
hole. בזמן שקשורים ותלויים, bizman shekshurim utluyim, now here's what makes them
defined part of the structure so it's not like you're adding to
the structure. They have to be tied to the structure and suspended,
meaning you could imagine that I've got, you know, this is the
door here to my house, it's a big plank I just use
to fill in the door, but I tie a rope from this
to the door, but it's still like lying on the floor, you
know what I mean? It's not in any way like suspended. It's
just, you know, it's tied so you don't go ahead and take
it away like the pens that at the bank are tied down,
you know what I mean? So it's connected, but it's not like
suspended. So still when you pick it off the floor and you
fill it up into your door, you're still it's more looks like
you're adding something. So even though physically it's connected, it's not it's
still somewhat construction like unless it actually, yeah, it's like the פקק
החלון. pkak hachalon. Like I said, it's actually quite interesting and I'm
only half kidding about writing a doctoral dissertation, the parallels between this
last פרק perek and issues that were discussed in the last פרק
perek of מסכת שבת. Masechet Shabbos. Okay, and you're absolutely correct. We
had like, for example, being caught without your without your wallet outside
of the city, so you know, here we have things about כתבי
הקודש kisvei hakodesh and your money and other stuff and getting it
back in and you know whatever and here we're talking about a
filling up with a temporary door and there we were talking about
filling up a window with a temporary stopper. Absolutely, yes, Charlie.
They're not mentioning שלוש טפחים shalosh tefachim or ארבע טפחים arba tefachim
here for לבוד? lavud?
It's not about לבוד, lavud, it's a part of the building. I
mean, if you have a huge door and you know, one part
of it, you know, is more than שלוש טפחים shalosh tefachim away
from your opening, it doesn't matter. It's on hinges and connected, it's
just part of the building. It's not לבוד lavud is about proximity.
לבוד lavud is about physically being part of the structure. Even when
we say like if a wall is close to the ground, it's
like it's connected, it's connected in the sense of continuity, like there's
not a break. It's not
connected— All right, so anyway, so if they are both tied to
it and suspended off somewhat, then נועלים בהן בשבת, no'elin bahen be-Shabbat,
you can lock use them to close the door on Shabbat. בין
בשבת בין ביום טוב, bein be-Shabbat bein be-Yom Tov, and certainly ביום
טוב. be-Yom Tov.
Now why is that a question? So the question is that it
does not say גבוהין מן הארץ. gevohin min ha-aretz. You could imagine
something that is like suspended in the sense like it's on hinges
or whatever, or it's on a rope and it's suspended, but it's
still like dragging. Right? There's a difference between lying flat and connected
by a rope, and being off of the ground. And you could
also have suspended, but it's a loose rope, so it's partly on
the ground and it's partly suspended. So this ברייתא braita does not
require that it be lifted off the ground. So what's the resolution?
So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, בשיש להם ציר, be-she-yesh lahem tzir, that
you do not need it to be suspended off the ground when
it has actually a hinge. If it's got a hinge, then that
more visually indicates that it's really part of the building, and then
you don't need the additional criteria of being suspended off of the
ground. Okay, that's what אביי Abaye says. So again, רש"י Rashi says
ולא מחזי כבונה, ve-lo mechezi ke-boneh, which raises a question here as
was raised constantly throughout מסכת שבת. Masechet Shabbat. It says don't do
this, don't do this, don't do that, what's דאורייתא de-Oraita and what's
דרבנן de-Rabbanan was never clear. But it sounds here that if there's
an issue
about visually it looks more part of the door, then clearly it
seems like we're in rabbinic territory. So if it's got a hinge,
at least once it's connected and suspended, so then once you have
a hinge, you don't need it to also be off of the
ground. That's what אביי Abaye says. רבא אמר, Rava amar, בשהיה להם
ציר. be-she-hayah lahem tzir. It doesn't even need a hinge now.
It just needs that there used to be a hinge. You know,
sometimes the door falls off and you're left with the hinge structure
behind. So as long as it has that hinge structure left behind,
it's, you know, people understand that this is conceptually a substitute door
and it's part of the building and not like you're adding a
new plank and you're constructing something on שבת. Shabbat. And in those
cases, you do not need it to also be suspended off of
the ground. All right, so let's take a look. מיתיבי, meitivi, they
ask on this.
We have a ברייתא braita that's almost a repeat of our משנה.
mishnah. בזמן שדלת הנגררת ומחצלת הנגררת וקנקן הנגרר, bizman she-delet ha-nigeret u-mechatzelet
ha-nigeret ve-kankan ha-nigrar, so you have these different cases about the door
or the mat. בזמן שקשורים ותלוים וגבוהים מן הארץ, bizman she-kshurim u-tluyim
u-gevohim min ha-aretz, and here it adds a third criteria: they are
tied and suspended and lifted off the ground. אפילו מלא נימא, afilu
melo nima, even if it's a hair's breadth, נועלים בהן, no'elin bahen,
you can lock with them. ואם לאו אין נועלים בהן, ve-im lav
ein no'elin bahen, and if not, you can't. So now, I don't
know why that's a question. That's just a restatement of the משנה.
mishnah. So which is, so fine, that's the case without the hinge,
which is what the גמרא Gemara basically says. אביי מתרץ לטעמיה ורבא
מתרץ לטעמיה, Abaye metaretz le-ta'ameh ve-Rava metaretz le-ta'ameh, each one explains according
to their reasoning. אביי מתרץ לטעמיה, Abaye metaretz le-ta'ameh, או שיש להם
ציר, o she-yesh lahem tzir, either if they have a hinge, או
שגבוהים מן הארץ, o she-gevohim min ha-aretz, or they're suspended off the
ground. רבא מתרץ לטעמיה, Rava metaretz le-ta'ameh, Rava says his reasoning, או
שהיה להם ציר, o she-hayah lahem tzir, either there was a hinge
and it's still obvious that there had been a hinge, או שגבוהים
מן הארץ, o she-gevohim min ha-aretz, or it's suspended off the ground.
So fine, no big finish. Basically, when it requires lifted off the
ground, it's when it does not, does not, or did not have
a hinge. תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. Okay, now another ברייתא braita about
this. סוכי קוצים וחבילין, sochei kotzim ve-chavilin, if you have like bundles
of thorns of like a, I don't know, a thorn bush, or
you have bundles of wood, and you're going to use them to
fill a hole, שהתקינם לפרצה, she-hitkinam le-pirtzah, you have set them aside
to fill up a hole in a wall שבחצר, she-ba-chatzer, that's a
wall in the courtyard, which makes more sense, by the way, than
a wall in your house, because you've got a wall in your
house and it's being filled up with a bundle of wood, you're
not protecting too much the stuff in your house. But okay, this
is using for a wall in the courtyard. בזמן שקשורים ותלוים, bizman
she-kshurim u-tluyim, so again it has this double criteria of tied and
suspended,
נועלים בהן, no'elin bahen, you can close with them on שבת. Shabbat.
And presumably that there's also a ציר, tzir, right, based on the
previous discussion, because that's why it's not paying attention to the concern
about lifted off of the ground. Okay, so but again, the idea
of tied and suspended. ואין צריך לומר ביום טוב, ve-ein tzarich lomar
be-Yom Tov, and it goes without saying on יום טוב. Yom Tov.
Fine. תני רבי חייא, tani Rabbi Chiyya, רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya taught,
דלת אלמנה, delet almanah, a widowed door, הנגררת, ha-nigeret, which drags, אין
נועלים בה, ein no'elin bah, you cannot lock with it. So what
does it mean that it is, that it's widowed? So again, so
presumably, now presumably there's something because of this widowed feature that makes
it not acceptable, which means otherwise it would be okay. So presumably
it's tied and it's suspended and maybe it's got the ציר, tzir,
right, the hinge, and all those things, normally, so tied and suspended
with a hinge, presumably that would be okay, but because it's somehow
less of a door then even with that it's not good. So
היכי דמי דלת אלמנה, heichi dami delet almanah, what is this widowed
door? So איכא דאמרי דחד שיפא, ika de-amri de-chad sheifa, some say
it means it's just one plank of wood. One plank of wood,
even if it has these qualities of tied and suspended and whatnot,
it looks more like you're sort of constructing something new than if
it actually is like a fashioned... door. You know, you basically have
a piece of plywood that you're just smacking up. Okay, and איכא
דאמרי ika d'amri some say דלית ליה גשמא, d'leit lei gashma, it
doesn't have a גשמא, gashma, which is a question of exactly what
it means, רש"י Rashi indicates that it's some type of a bar
that would connect it to the door, maybe like a, maybe like
a handle or something. Some say it means that there's not a
threshold below for it to fit into. But it's missing some type
of a feature that even though it is tied and suspended, it
still looks more like you're doing an act of construction. אמר רב
יהודה. Amar Rav Yehuda.
It just means that it's lacking an important feature. Like a woman
who is bereaved of her husband.
Is it working?
Is it—it's working, it's functional. I mean, the idea, for example, that
it's one plank of wood, you know, means it totally fills the
hole, but it's not like it's crafted as a door. So yeah,
I mean, I don't know, we can do other explanations, that like
it's missing some type of a bolt or a bar is like
it actually lost, you know, it's—of something fell off of it. So
it's—yeah. I don't mean defective in a bad way, it's lacking something.
Something that was a part of it is no longer a part
of it. That's at least—that's—but it doesn't fit for the context of
the single plank.
No, but the handle doesn't make any sense either.
It's not like your thorn bush has a handle or whatever it
is you're using. Yeah, I don't—that's why I didn't understand רש"י Rashi
so well. So I think some explain that it's not about—it's not
about a bar or a handle, but it's more like some type
of a—that the door frame doesn't have a threshold like, so, you
know, a good—like a good frame on the bottom. All right, anyway,
תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Where are we? תני רבי חייא, Tani Rabbi
Chiya, we just said. אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, האי מדורתא
hai medurta ממעלה למעלה—so mimala l'malla this is a very interesting הלכה.
halacha. Since the משנה Mishna talks about things that look like building,
here's a series of הלכות halachot that are things that you would
never think would be a problem on שבת Shabbat and יום טוב,
Yom Tov, but actually are because they look like building. So האי
מדורתא, hai medurta, if you're making a—a, you know, a—a fire or
a pile of wood, a fire pile. Now this is יום טוב,
Yom Tov, not שבת, Shabbat, so you're allowed to do that. Okay,
so ממעלה למטה mimalla l'mata שרי, shari, if you do it from
top down it's okay. ממטה למעלה mimatta l'mala אסור, assur, from bottom
up it's forbidden. Because what do you do when you make a
wood pile? You know, you basically like, I don't know, it's been
a while since I've been in the Boy Scouts, actually never actually
was in the Boy Scouts, but okay, anyway. You know, you sort
of go ahead and you like do things like this, and then
you do something like this, right? You sort of make like a
whole structure, right? And you like, you know, you pile the stuff
up, but it's in a very type of a crisscross structure. So
that's בונה, boneh, you're building up walls of something. Okay, so the
basically the principle is going to be like this. You can build
some—you can build—if you are building some structure, even if it's not
really like a structure, even if it's something that's really almost like,
you know, an object, but you're—but you are basically building walls up
from the bottom, which is דרך בנין, derech binyan, that's technically forbidden.
What you can do is you can start on the top and
go ahead and build underneath it. Now there are a lot of—now
when is—if that were always a problem, you can start imagining a
million things that you're not allowed to do. We'll get to that
in a minute. Let's read the cases and then I'll talk about
the practical implications, okay?
But how are you doing it from the top down?
Oh, that's actually a good point. I guess you have to hold
one level and somebody else does the level below it and then
you lower it down. Like you do it in stages, I suppose.
Like a fireplace where you put the big logs on first and
then tuck underneath where you want the kindling?
Oh, okay. I guess you could do that in that scenario. All
right, so okay. So ממטה למעלה mimatta l'mala אסור, assur, from bottom
up it's forbidden. וכן ביצתא, vechein beiza, if you are eggs and
you're making a pile of eggs, like you're in a—that would sound
crazy, right? Like you're filling it up into a basket. Okay, or
רש"י Rashi says, or רש"י Rashi says on a griddle, right, רש"י
Rashi says not in the basket. Okay, what? So yeah, so רש"י
Rashi says either you're piling them on a griddle or that you
want to have like, it says על גבי שני עצים שמקיפין זו
את זו. al gabei shenei eitzim shemakkifin zu et zu.
Right, so I'm sorry, רש"י Rashi says not eggs on top of
one another. רש"י Rashi basically says that you basically are trying to
put eggs on a fire. So you want to put them on
top of—on top of like some—like crisscrossed stuff of—of twigs. You hold
the egg and you make the crisscross of twigs underneath it, rather
than the reverse. וכן קדירה, vechein kedira,
and similarly if you are—if you are basically taking—taking a—a pot. And
the way you would have a pot over a fire, this is
assuming on יום טוב, Yom Tov, is you would take let's say
two barrels or two things that you're going to use as walls,
and then you put the pot in the hollow that's created between
them and you put the fire underneath. So similarly you hold the
pot and then you bring the barrels to the side, rather than
the opposite.
Is this supposed to be a שינוי? shinui?
A שינוי, shinui, yeah. And it's not דרך בנין derech binyan would
be another way. Because you're building—to build some type of a structure
from bottom up is a problem. וכן פורייא, vechein purya, a bed.
If you have a bed that basically first you go ahead and
you like, you know, it's a collapsible bed, but first you undo
the—the frame structure and then you put the mattress. On top, that's
a problem. What you have to do is you have to hold
the mattress and then put the frame structure underneath. וכן חביתא, vechen
chavita, and similarly barrels, which רש"י Rashi basically says and this is
similar to what I was saying before about the eggs, that basically
you're piling barrels on top, two barrels and a third barrel on
top of them, that's like building a structure from the ground up.
Now, say you really can't do any of that, so then the
question becomes תוספות Tosafot asks this question. So you mean basically on
שבת, Shabbat, if I'm learning my ספרים sefarim here, I can't like
pile up my ספרים sefarim like this, right? Is that what you're
really telling me? I mean I can't do anything that's just like
placing objects from the bottom up that creates some type of a
structure? So take a look at תוספות Tosafot here, this little תוספות
Tosafot gives us some limits on this, some qualifications. He says,
וכן ביצה פירש בקונטרס שסידר ביצים על כלי ברזל שקורין גרידל ובלע"ז
ואין נראה לי דאין דרך בנין בכך. vechen beitza pirash bekuntres shesider
beitzim al kli barzel shekorin gridel uvel'az ve'ein nireh li de'ein derech
binyan bekach. He says to put it on an existing grid, like
on a structure, to put an egg
on top of some type of a structure, they're not even building
up the walls.
ולא דמו למחיצות ופוריא דמסדר זו אצל זו. velo damu lemchitzot upuraya
demesader zu etzel zu. First criteria he says is it's not a
problem, normally we have a מחיצה mechitza problem, a שבת Shabbat בנין
binyan problem if I make a roof. So if I've got let's
say a canopy frame on my bed and I put the canopy
on top of it, that actually would be a בנין binyan problem
on שבת Shabbat because I've made a roof. But there it's functioning
as a roof. Here, the stuff is not functioning as a roof.
You're making piles of eggs and piles of sticks. So תוספות Tosafot
says criterion number one for this to be a problem is that
you're not just putting the top on but you're actually building the
whole thing with the walls from the bottom up. That's case number
one. Now we still haven't explained piling up books, why that's not
an issue. Okay, so then he says like this: ותדעי דהרי היתר
פשוט הוא, vetedei daharei heter pashut hu, you should know that it's
taken as completely accepted as acceptable, להניח קדירה אגב טרפידא, lehaniach kdeirah
agav tarpida, to put a pot on a tripod, טרפידא, tarpida, okay?
ונראה לי לפרש שסידר עצים או ביצים ומניח ביצה על גביהן ומה
שאנו מסדרים כיכר, venireh li lefareish shesider eitzim o beitzim umaneach beitza
al gabeihen umah she'anu mesadrim kikar, and that's how he explains the
case of the ביצה beitza that you actually build up the walls,
ומה שאנו מסדרים כיכר מכאן וכיכר מכאן וכיכר גביהן, umah she'anu mesadrim
kikar mikan vekikar mikan vekikar gabeihen, how about the fact that we
like pile up loaves of bread or pile up books, how is
that not a problem, you're building the walls? So he says, או
בספר לית איסורא אלא כשצריך לאוויר שתחתיהן. o besefer leit issura ela
keshetzarich la'avir shetachteihen. So תוספות Tosafot says second criteria which is not
so clear in the cases in the גמרא, Gemara, especially if you
think one of the cases is barrels and one of the cases
is a bed, but he basically says you're creating it to some
degree to serve as a type of an אהל. ohel. In what
way? You don't want it as a structure and as a canopy
but you want to use the space underneath. So for example if
you're thinking about the barrels and the pots, you want to use
the space that's created underneath because you want to light a fire
and you want that heat to be trapped. So that's a case
that maybe in the case of the firewood you're also trying to
create that space in the middle, that sort of vacuum, not vacuum
but whatever, the space between the walls because that'll be good for
ventilation and it'll be good for heating the fire. So that's when
it's a problem. But if you're just piling things, there's no sense
of building there and it's not a problem. He says, אי נמי
לא דמו לבנין אלא כשעושה על גבי קרקע ולא על השולחן, ee
nami lo damu lebinyan ela keshe'oseh al gabei karka velo al hashulchan,
which is also a nice answer. It's not בנין binyan if you're
just piling stuff on a table. We're talking about you're piling them
on the ground. Okay, so there are these two three important criteria
that תוספות Tosafot adds to make this more reasonable. Number one is
only when you're building the walls, that's when you have to worry
top-down rather than bottom-up. Number two is that it's not just piling
things in the sense that they happen to be on top of
one another but you're actually trying to use the space created between
them.
Or an alternative way that it's not a problem is that it's
on the table rather, and this would only be a problem if
it were being built on the ground. Okay, moving right along.
So like even does it have to be a number of eggs
or just even one egg? Like let's say I want
to put down an egg? No, no, I don't want to deal
with eggs because we don't פוסקין pasken and it's too extreme. אמר
ליה ההוא צדוקי, Amar lei hahu Tzadoki, you gotta move or like
אמר ליה ההוא צדוקי, Amar lei hahu Tzadoki, so a certain Sadducee,
okay, that's sometimes probably which is clearly a what do you call
it, almost always a
גירסא, girsa, right,
מינא mina or מין, min, actually מינא mina really I think, anyway,
or according to some of the גירסא, girsa, גוי goy or something,
okay, anyway, or מינא, mina, but anyway a certain either Sadducee or
heretic, which sometimes can mean a Jewish Christian, said רבי יהושע בן
חנניה, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya, חדקא, chadka, you are like dust or
like a grounded stuff, that's how you're compared. דכתיב וכו', dichtiv vechu,
it says regarding you, טובם כחדק, tovam kechedek, the good one, I'm
sorry, no, חדק chedek here's understood because it says חדקים שבפרצה chadakim
shebepirtza in our משנה. Mishnah. So חדקים chadakim refer to like thorns.
So you're thorny people because it says by you their best are
like the thorns. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said back to
him, טיפשא, tipsha, and often by the way when it's disputes about
interpretations of פסוקים pesukim it often does relate to early Jewish Christians.
So anyway he said to you, טיפשא. tipsha. You know idiot שפיל
לסיפיה דקרא Shpil l'seifei d'kora look at the end of the פסוק
Pasuk דכתיב De-ketiv ישר ממסוכה Yashar mi-mesukha straighter is you know
more straight than מסוכה Mesukha which is here being read as like
סוכה Sukha something that is protected. ואלא מאי טובם כחדק V'ela mai
tovam k'chedek what does that mean? כשם שחדקים הללו מגינים על הפרצה
K'shem she-chadakim halalu meginim al ha-pirtzah and that's the connection to our
משנה. Mishnah. The same way you could use like a bundle of
thorns to protect
in a to fill up a hole. By the way you might
understand why they wanted to use thorns because of the point I
was making about security concerns. It's like barbed wire. You know you
fill up your hole with thorns people are going to try to
avoid it even if there's no lock on the door. Okay so
the same way that's true about thorns so כך טובים שבנו מגינים
עלינו Kach tovim she-banu meginim aleinu protect us
and that's like ממסוכה Mi-mesukha something that is protective like a סוכה
Sukkah like a protection. Okay דבר אחר Davar acher another explanation טובם
כחדק Tovam k'chedek שמחדקין את הרשעים She-machadikin et ha-reshaim that they
so this is חדק Chedek you know to like to turn into
dust that they trample and make into dust the evil ones and
some here say the non-Jews לגיהנום L'Gehennom into גיהנום Gehennom or that
are in גיהנום Gehennom שנאמר She-ne'emar קומי ודושי בת ציון Kumi v'dushi
bat Tziyon
rise up and trample oh daughter of Zion כי קרנך אשים ברזל
Ki kornach asim barzel I will make your horn into iron ופרסותיך
אשים נחושה U-parsotayich asim nechusha and your and your hooves into into
a brass והדיקות עמים רבים V'hadikot amim rabim
and you will trample or turn into dust the many nations. So
basically a way of saying you're going to get it in the
end stop making fun of us. Okay next משנה Mishnah לא יעמוד
אדם ברשות היחיד Lo ya'amod adam bi-reshut ha-yachid
now back to things having somewhat to do with domains. A person
should not stand in the private domain ויפתח ברשות הרבים V'yiftach bi-reshut
ha-rabim
and open up his door into and this is with a key
into the רשות הרבים. Reshut ha-Rabim. Okay why? Because now when the
problem is not that the door is connected but the problem is
that you've got your key. Okay and this is you might remember
we were saying for a few days that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
disagreed with the idea that you could reach into another domain and
manipulate. So here would be here is the רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
position. Here's my door right I'm standing here right in in the
רשות הרבים Reshut ha-Rabim this is my house okay and I have
my key let's say by you know right in my front porch
and some I don't know it's surrounded by walls it's all in
a under the door mat but it's all surrounded by walls it's
רשות היחיד. Reshut ha-Yachid. I'm leaning in from the רשות הרבים Reshut
ha-Rabim picking up my key opening my door okay and I'm manipulating
an object from the רשות הרבים Reshut ha-Rabim in the רשות היחיד.
Reshut ha-Yachid. I'm not allowed what are you supposed to do? What
walk into the רשות היחיד.
Reshut ha-Yachid. Keys were very big we know.
Yes yeah right they used to just stand in the doorway.
Yeah it will get into the right. ברשות הרבים
ויפתח ברשות היחיד Bi-reshut ha-rabim v'yiftach bi-reshut ha-yachid so you can't stand
in רשות היחיד Reshut ha-Yachid and open something in רשות הרבים Reshut
ha-Rabim or vice versa אלא אם כן עשה מחיצה גבוהה עשרה טפחים
Ela im ken asa mechitzah gevoha asara tefachim unless you basically make
a wall of ten טפחים Tefachim this is for רשות היחיד Reshut
ha-Yachid and basically you're standing in a רשות היחיד Reshut ha-Yachid and
then you can you know make a fence around your porch and
stand on your porch okay דברי רבי מאיר. Divrei Rabbi Meir. That's
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and this is the רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
we were quoting earlier that says not like you manipulating objects in
another domain. אמרו לו Amru lo the sages said back to him
מעשה בשוק של פטמין Ma'aseh be-shuk shel patamin there was a story
there was a case in the marketplace of פטמין Patamin which is
like a you know fattened like geese or chicken or fat like
you know so so the the butcher place a marketplace שהיו בירושלים
She-hayu b'Yerushalayim
that was in ירושלים Yerushalayim שהיו נועלים ומניחים את המפתח בחלון שעל
גבי הפתח She-hayu no'alim u-manichim et ha-mafte'ach b'chalon she-al gabei ha-petach
that they would lock up their stores and or whatever they would
lock up and they would put up the put the key on
the
in the window above the doorway. So you know that whole idea
of hiding it like you know under the window in the windowsill
it's an old thing. Anyway and presumably this שוק Shuk would be
a רשות הרבים Reshut ha-Rabim and presumably what they would do is
that they would take the key from the windowsill which is רשות
היחיד Reshut ha-Yachid and you know somehow open up the window or
open some door and they'd be manipulating it within a רשות היחיד
Reshut ha-Yachid zone while standing in a רשות הרבים. Reshut ha-Rabim.
If it's the market what are they doing buying and selling?
Well I don't know not necessarily using the market but whatever maybe
it's the you know I right I don't know maybe it's their
private homes are also you know opened up into the marketplace. רבי
יוסי אומר Rabbi Yossi omer now רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says שוק
של צמרים היה Shuk shel tzemarim haya which is okay that was
helpful. He said it wasn't they weren't selling chickens they were selling
wool a wool marketplace but maybe it's important just to you know
verify the details you know he says I actually tell you I
do know that story and just to get the facts straight it
was a wool marketplace not a chicken marketplace. Okay ורבנן V'rabbanan so
the
rabbis so ורבנן V'rabbanan אמר רבי מאיר Amar Rabbi Meir says the
גמרא Gemara רשות הרבים ומהדרינהו כרמלית Reshut ha-Rabim u-mahadreinhu karmelit so the
גמרא Gemara doesn't get it because the גמרא Gemara
assumes that well because and it's going to tell us why in
a minute that
even the marketplaces in ירושלים Yerushalayim because ירושלים Yerushalayim was surrounded with
walls so even the marketplaces worse would be would be a כרמלית
Karmelit even the marketplaces... if you had a very public space, if
it's surrounded with walls, the worst it is is a כרמלית carmelis
and therefore the fact that you can stand in a כרמלית carmelis
and manipulate an object in a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid
does not necessarily good evidence against Rabbi Meir who talks about רשות
הרבים reshus harabbim and manipulating in רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. So רבנן
אמרו רבי מאיר רשות הרבים, Rabbanan amru Rabbi Meir reshus harabbim, he's
talking about a real biblical domain. ומהדר אינהו כרמלית? umahadar inhu carmelis?
And they're responding to him with a כרמלית? carmelis? Because ירושלים Yerushalayim
was a כרמלית, carmelis, even the marketplaces. דאמר רבה בר בר חנה
אמר רבי יוחנן D'amar Rabba bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan and
we're talking about echoing, harkening back to early discussions in, this was
actually in עירובין Eruvin as well. Okay, because רבה בר בר חנה
Rabba bar bar Chana says in the
name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, ירושלים אלמלא דלתותיה ננעלות בלילה חייבין
עליה משום רשות הרבים. Yerushalayim ilmalei daltoteha ninalot balailah chayavin aleha mishum
reshus harabbim. It would be a רשות הרבים reshus harabbim although it's
surrounded by walls, but if the basically the main streets go through
the walls and those streets are not sealed off at night, then
the walls don't count enough to you know to change its status
from רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. Okay, but what are we saying? But
now that the doors are locked at night, it actually is no
longer רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. So at worst it's a כרמלית. carmelis.
So what type of evidence are you bringing from the marketplace in
ירושלים Yerushalayim which was a כרמלית? carmelis?
So אמר רב פפא כאן קודם שנפרצו בו פרצות כאן לאחר שנפרצו
בו פרצות. Amar Rav Pappa kan kodem shenifretzu bo pratzot kan l'achar
shenifretzu bo pratzot. Okay, but what state are the walls in? Right?
If it's before the walls have been breached by the non-Jews and
they're real walls, then you're right, then and you lock those walls
at night, then it's a רשות... then it's not a רשות הרבים.
reshus harabbim But after the walls have had multiple breaches, it stops,
then it goes back to really being the marketplaces to really being
רשות הרבים reshus harabbim because the walls no longer are real walls
anymore. Which is quite interesting because you know as far as I
know and people who know the history of this period better will
correct me, I don't think that there were any serious breaches in
the walls from the time of the חורבן הבית churban bayis from
the Romans till the time through the period of the משנה Mishnah
and the גמרא, Gemara, right? Were there any other breaches in the
walls? No. So you know so this statement of ירושלים Yerushalayim was
no longer רשות הרבים reshus harabbim. because of the doors, I guess
what the גמרא Gemara is saying is that all was meant pre-
you know pre- חורבן הבית. churban bayis. That was all like harking
back to this pre- חורבן הבית churban bayis time. But in modern
times, which we're talking about and in which the משנה Mishnah was
talking about, ירושלים Yerushalayim could have real רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim, Okay,
modern times. Right. Exactly. Post- חורבן הבית. churban bayis. So אמר... amar...
okay, so that's the answer. Now אימא סיפא, eima seifa, let us,
oh, sorry. ורבא אמר סיפא אתיא לשערי גינה. V'Rava amar seifa asya
l'sharei gina. No, you know what? It is true. They are bringing
evidence from a כרמלית. carmelis. They are assuming that the marketplace is
a כרמלית. carmelis. But nevertheless, Rabbi Meir doesn't even allow a כרמלית
carmelis situation. He, when he says you can't open a door and
standing in a different domain, that's even if it's a doorway to
a like garden. So you're not standing in the street.
You're standing in רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, רשות היחיד?
reshus hayachid? Right. So we'll see what the גמרא Gemara reads it.
But even if you're standing in a garden and trying to open
the doorway, so it's a כרמלית. carmelis. Even that Rabbi Meir would
say a problem and that's the evidence they bring from the marketplaces
in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. והכי קתני, Vehachi katani, and this is what he's
saying. וכן לא יעמוד אדם ברשות היחיד ויפתח בכרמלית בכרמלית ויפתח ברשות
היחיד. Vechein lo yaamod adam b'reshus hayachid veyiftach b'carmelis b'carmelis veyiftach b'reshus
hayachid.
So sticks in a whole line that's missing, right? And saying, yeah,
Rabbi Meir also, the same way he wouldn't allow רשות הרבים, Reshus
HaRabbim, he also wouldn't allow a כרמלית. carmelis. אלא אם כן, Ella
im kein, top of ק"א ע"ב, kuf aleph amud beis, אלא אם
כן עשה מחיצה גבוהה עשרה טפחים, ella im kein asa mechitzah gevohah
asarah tfechim,
unless you're yourself in a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. דברי רבי מאיר,
Divrei Rabbi Meir, that's what Rabbi Meir says. אמרו לו מעשה בשוק
של פטמין שהיו בירושלים שהיו נועלין ומניחין מפתח בחלון שעל גבי הפתח.
Amru lo maaseh beshuk shel pataimin shehayu b'Yerushalayim shehayu noalin u'manichin mafteiach
bechalon sheal gabai hapesach. רבי יוסי אומר שוק של צמרים היה. Rabbi
Yosei omer shuk shel tzamarin hayah. Fine.
So basically he just says, yeah, Rabbi Meir also would argue by
a כרמלית carmelis and that's why they're bringing evidence from the case
of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. But this is the Rabbi Meir we were talking
about before that does not like you manipulating objects in another domain,
and here we're saying even if you're standing only in a כרמלית,
carmelis, not even in any biblical domain. תנו רבנן. Tnu rabbanan. פתחי
שערי גינה. Pitchai shaarei gina.
Now we're going back to this garden
gate because which are כרמלית carmelis cases. So you have the openings
for the gates of a garden. בזמן שיש להם בית שער מבפנים,
Bizman sheyesh lahem beis shaar mipifnim, פותח ונועל מבפנים, poteach ve'noel mipifnim,
you can open it towards the inside. מבחוץ פותח ונועל מבחוץ, Mibachutz
poteach ve'noel mibachutz, and on the outside you can open it towards
the outside. מכאן ומכאן, Mikan umikan, on both sides, פותח ונועל מכאן
ומכאן, poteach ve'noel mikan umikan, you can do it either way, which
basically means, right?
Pen and paper, I got to draw. So anyway, okay. Here's your
gate, here's your שער. shaar. Okay, and you know, and if you
have here like right inside of it, I'd have to draw but
I'm not going to. Anyway, a gatehouse, okay, it's inside, it didn't
go straight into the garden, and you're standing in the gatehouse, right?
Then you can open up the door and open it in because,
you know, you're bringing it into like a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid.
You know, or similarly, if it has a gatehouse out here and
you're standing right here, right? You can maybe stick your hand in
and open... but you are
manipulating the
object in the
רשות היחיד, Reshus HaYachid, you're sticking your hand, let's say it would
be easier to see it that way, okay, you stick your hand
into the into the little gatehouse, you pick up the key in
the gatehouse, you open up the door, right? even though you're standing
in the רשות הרבים, Reshus HaRabbim, you're manipulating everything in the רשות
היחיד. Reshus HaYachid. Okay. Okay. אין להם
לא
כאן ולא כאן,
Ein Lahem Lo
Kan V'lo Kan, so אסורין, Asurin, if there's no gatehouse either
way, so you can't because, you know, the key you'll be picking
up will be somehow in a, you'll be picking it up in
a כרמלית. Karmelis. And that's going to be a problem because presumably,
you know, then you put it in. If you take a look
at רשי, Rashi, רשי Rashi explains לא כאן ולא כאן אסורין מכן
ומכן, Lo Kan V'lo Kan Asurin Mikan u'Mikan, like five lines down
in רשי. Rashi. He says דמנעל רשות היחיד הוא. De-Manul Reshus HaYachid
Hu. The lock itself that's in the door, okay, and this is
an important point that has not yet been stated, the lock itself
is a רשות היחיד. Reshus HaYachid. ואף על פי שהמפתח מונח עליו,
Ve-Af Al Pi She-HaMaftayach Munach Alav, גזר רבי מאיר שלא יעמוד ברשות
הרבים ולא בגינה ויטול מפתח של רשות היחיד שמא יביאנו אצלו לרשות
הרבים או לכרמלית. Gazar Rabbi Meir She-Lo Ya'amod Be-Reshus HaRabbim Ve-Lo Be-Gina
Ve-Yitol Maftayach Shel Reshus HaYachid Shema Yevi'enu Etzlo Le-Reshus HaRabbim Oh Le-Karmelis.
Right,
so this is רשי Rashi saying that this is רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. So רשי Rashi basically understands that this case is that when
said that if you can go in the gatehouse, it wasn't the
case I said which could have been the Rabbis that you're leaning
in. It actually means you can physically enter the gatehouse and be
in a רשות היחיד. Reshus HaYachid. So then it's not much of
a חידוש. Chidush. But basically, here is your door and you have
like a whole lock contraption, let's say, you know, you have a
lock contraption on the door, okay, and this is a רשות היחיד.
Reshus HaYachid. It's connected to the to the arch, the arch extends
טפחים Tefachim by ארבע טפחים, Arba Tefachim, whatever, the whole thing is
רשות היחיד Reshus HaYachid and this is your lock and contraption. And
you keep the key on top of it. And you're standing here.
So if you're standing in a gatehouse or in a רשות היחיד,
Reshus HaYachid, fine, everything is taking place in a רשות היחיד. Reshus
HaYachid. But this is רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So if you're not
standing in a gatehouse, if you're here in a כרמלית, Karmelis, right,
it's even a גינה, Gina, it's even not a רשות הרבים, Reshus
HaRabbim even the street you're standing in is a כרמלית, Karmelis, it's
a גינה, Gina, okay, and you're taking the key off of the
box, which is in a רשות היחיד, Reshus HaYachid, and you're putting
it in the hole, which is a רשות היחיד, Reshus HaYachid, and
you're completely manipulating it in רשות היחיד Reshus HaYachid zone. Since you're
standing in a כרמלית, Karmelis, since there is no gatehouse, right? If
there were a gatehouse you'd be in the רשות היחיד. Reshus HaYachid.
But since there is not, that is a problem, that is רבי
מאיר's Rabbi Meir problem. Okay. And this again is the gate, is
the case of the כרמלית Karmelis which supports the idea before that
they argue even about the כרמלית. Karmelis.
So, אין להם, Ein Lahem, let me read that again, אין להם
לא כאן ולא כאן, Ein Lahem Lo Kan Ve-Lo Kan, if they
don't have gatehouses on either side and you are actually standing in
the כרמלית, Karmelis, אסורין כאן וכאן, Asurin Kan Ve-Kan, then it's forbidden
to take the key and open up the lock and basically even
though you're all manipulating in רשות היחיד Reshus HaYachid zone. וכן חנויות
הפתוחות לרשות הרבים Ve-Chen Chanuyos Ha-Petuchos Le-Reshus HaRabbim
and similarly if you have door stores that open up into רשות
הרבים Reshut HaRabim and again they have a type of a, you
know, of a lock, of a lock box, lock contraption on the
door. בזמן שהמנעול למטה מעשרה, Bi-Zman She-HaManul Lemata Me-Asarah,
if this whole contraption is below עשרה טפחים, Asarah Tefachim, then מביא
מפתח מערב שבת ומניחה באיסקופא, Mevi Maftayach Me-Erev Shabbos U'Menichah Be-Iskopa,
then you can take the, you then you can take a key
from before שבת, Shabbos, you put it on the איסקופא Iskopa which
is the, which is the what do you call it? the patio,
the porch. למחר פותח ונועל ומחזירו לאיסקופא. Le-Machar Potayach Ve-No'el U'Machziro Le-Iskopa.
The next day you can go ahead and open it up and
put it back onto the כרמלית. Karmelis. So basically what you've got
here is then you're manipulating everything into in a כרמלית, Karmelis, right?
If you are here and this is actually here's your door, here's
your חנות, Chanut, your store, but this locking mechanism is below עשרה
טפחים. Asarah Tefachim. So below עשרה טפחים Asarah Tefachim it's not a
רשות היחיד, Reshus HaYachid, the locking mechanism. So you're standing in the
כרמלית Karmelis and you can go ahead and you can take it,
as you're on the, you're on the what is it? What is
it called? The איסקופא, Iskopa, the, you know, the the
the porch, and you know, you have your key hidden somewhere here
under the mat, okay, so fine, so you take it from the
כרמלית Karmelis and you open up the locking mechanism in a כרמלית
Karmelis and everything is in a כרמלית. Karmelis. Yes.
Why did the store not have the, they're not likely to have?
Yeah,
I really don't know. Maybe the stores were more likely to have
these mechanisms
lower. Yeah, you left something in the store. It's your store, you
need to get something out of it. You need, you know, you
want some fruit or something. I don't know. But maybe also they
would more often lock their stores more than they would lock their
houses. I really don't know. Clearly, there was something relevant, you know,
that made it more of a reasonable scenario.
Are these actually tied to like the lock and would רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir still have a problem where you say לא פלוג? Lo
Pelug?
Probably say לא פלוג, Lo Pelug, that's interesting, you know, that may
be, I don't know, it's interesting because maybe you could say maybe
it's not even seen as part of the house. Okay, so let's
take a look. So רש״י *Rashi* actually says, רש״י *Rashi* actually answers
your question as he says שערי חנויות פעמים שהן גבוהים ופעמים שהן
נמוכים ולפיכך נתנו בהן חילוק *Sha'arei chanuyot pe'amim shehen gevohim u-fe'amim shehen
nemuchim u-le-fichach natnu vahen chiluk*. So רש״י *Rashi* actually says that דוקא
*davka* the store lock mechanism sometimes are low and sometimes are high
and therefore they provided an interesting illustration of this case. You know,
maybe the gate mechanism than the house mechanisms are always עשרה טפחים
tfachim *asara tefachim* high, whereas the stores allow you to talk about
how high the locking mechanism. Okay. So... Okay. בזמן שהמנעול למטה מעשרה
מביא מפתח mafteiach, מערב שבת Shabbat, ומניחו באיסקופה *bizman she-hamanil lemata me-asara
mevi mafte'ach me-erev Shabbat u-menicho be-iskopa*.
So you put the key under the mat and that's a כרמלית
Karmelit *karmelit*. למחר פותח ונועל ומחזירו לאיסקופה *lemachar pote'ach ve-no'el u-machziro la-iskopa*
and then you open it up and then you put it back
and everything is being within כרמלית Karmelit *karmelit* zone so you're good
even according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*. ובזמן שהמנעול למעלה
מעשרה *u-bizman she-hamanil lemala me-asara*, but if the whole locking mechanism is
higher than עשרה טפחים tfachim, *asara tefachim* and presumably it's again not
clear why higher is enough, what happened to the four walls? But
anyway, somehow for higher than עשרה *asara*, now it's a רשות היחיד
Reshut HaYachid, *reshut ha-yachid*. So then what do you do? בזמן שהמנעול
למעלה מעשרה מביא מפתח מערב שבת Shabbat, ומניחו במנעול *bizman she-hamanil lemala
me-asara mevi mafte'ach me-erev Shabbat u-menicho ba-manul*, you bring your key from
before שבת Shabbat. *Shabbat* and you actually put it in the locking
mechanism. למחר פותח ונועל ומחזירו למקומו דברי רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *lemachar
pote'ach ve-no'el u-machziro limekomo divrei Rabbi Meir*. And then you open it
up and then you put it back, I don't know why you
put it back, it was already in the in the מנעול *manul*.
But
so the question is going to be why you can do this
because you're standing in a כרמלית Karmelit *karmelit* and why you can
manipulate it. So we'll take a look. Hold on one moment let
me just check רש״י *Rashi*. Okay. דברי רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *divrei
Rabbi Meir*, that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says. וחכמים
אומרים אף בזמן שהמנעול למעלה מעשרה טפחים tfachim מביא מפתח מערב שבת
ומניחו באיסקופה *ve-Chachamim omrim af bizman she-hamanil lemala me-asara tefachim mevi mafte'ach
me-erev Shabbat u-menicho be-iskopa*. You can go ahead and put the, you
can take the key from before שבת *Shabbat* and put it in
on the door, on the like balcony, not balcony, whatever, on the
porch. למחר פותח ונועל ומחזירו למקומו *lemachar pote'ach ve-no'el u-machziro limekomo* and
then the next day you can go ahead and open it, open
the door, או בחלון שעל גבי הפתח *o be-chalon she-al gabei ha-petach*
and then put it back either on the porch or on the
top of the lock, או בחלון שעל גבי הפתח *o be-chalon she-al
gabei ha-petach*, or into the window that's open, that's by the door.
אם יש בחלון *im yesh be-chalon*, now, אם יש בחלון *im yesh
be-chalon*, that's if the window is smaller than ארבעה על ארבעה *arba'a
al arba'a*, it's a מקום פטור makom p'tur *makom patur*. ואם יש
בחלון ארבעה על ארבעה אסור assur. *ve-im yesh be-chalon arba'a al arba'a
asur*, but if the window is four-by-four, then it's forbidden, then it's
a רשות היחיד Reshut HaYachid. *reshut ha-yachid* and then it's forbidden מפני
שהוא כמוציא מרשות לרשות *mipnei she-hu ke-motzi me-reshut li-reshut* because it's like
you're going from one domain to the other, you're going from the
כרמלית Karmelit *karmelit* to the רשות היחיד Reshut HaYachid. *reshut ha-yachid*. So
the question here is why is everybody okay when this thing is
higher than עשרה *asara*, why isn't it still a רשות היחיד Reshut
HaYachid. *reshut ha-yachid* problem, meaning why is it only the window or
whatever that is a problem? Let me just double check רש״י *Rashi*
one second, make sure I'm explaining this correctly. Right, okay, yes.
Okay. So right, רש״י *Rashi* says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going
to say that this, that so basically let me describe the other
case and then deal with the implication. So it says כיוון דבלא
עשרה טפחים tfachim *keivan de-belo asara tefachim*, then it's all okay you're
all within a כרמלית Karmelit. *karmelit*. Let's say however the locking mechanism
is higher than עשרה טפחים tfachim *asara tefachim* and it's a רשות
היחיד Reshut HaYachid? *reshut ha-yachid*. Okay, so then what does the משנה
mishna. *Mishna* say, what does רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* say
in that case, the ברייתא braita *beraita* let's read it again? It
says, where are we? ובזמן שהמנעול למעלה מעשרה מביא מפתח מערב שבת
ומניחו במנעול למחר פותח ונועל ומחזירו למקומו דברי רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
*u-bizman she-hamanil lemala me-asara mevi mafte'ach me-erev Shabbat u-menicho ba-manul lemachar pote'ach
ve-no'el u-machziro limekomo divrei Rabbi Meir* that you can actually have the
key here and you use it on שבת *Shabbat* even though you're
standing in a כרמלית Karmelit. *karmelit*. So what happened רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir *Rabbi Meir*, you're supposed to not like it when you're standing
in a כרמלית Karmelit, *karmelit* manipulating it. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is going to say, ah, in this ברייתא braita? *beraita* it seems
that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* has reversed himself and feels
that we're not going to make the, it won't be a problem
in a כרמלית Karmelit *karmelit* situation. It's only a problem in a
רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim *reshut ha-rabim* situation. So רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*
is actually going to be okay to stand in a כרמלית Karmelit
*karmelit* and take the key off the box and manipulate it in
a רשות היחיד Reshut HaYachid. *reshut ha-yachid*. That's the only way we're
going to explain that. But now let's understand the חכמים Chachamim *Chachamim*.
That's רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*'s case. Now what do the חכמים Chachamim
*Chachamim* say? דברי רבי מאיר *divrei Rabbi Meir*. וחכמים אומרים אף בזמן
שהמנעול למעלה מעשרה טפחים tfachim מביא מפתח מערב שבת ומניחו באיסקופה *ve-Chachamim
omrim af bizman she-hamanil lemala me-asara tefachim mevi mafte'ach me-erev Shabbat u-menicho
be-iskopa*. You can go ahead and put the, you can take the
key from before שבת *Shabbat* and put it in on the door,
on the like balcony, not balcony, whatever, on the porch. למחר פותח
ונועל ומחזירו למקומו או בחלון שעל גבי הפתח *lemachar pote'ach ve-no'el u-machziro
limekomo o be-chalon she-al gabei ha-petach*. So they're going to have you
presumably take the key from the איסקופה *iskopa* which is a כרמלית
Karmelit, *karmelit* and open up the door. Okay. So how does that
work? So let me just one
second. Right.
One minute, hold
on. ומניחו במנעול... ומניחו באיסקופה למחר פותח ונועל ומחזירו למקומו או בחלון
שעל גבי פתח *u-menicho ba-manul... u-menicho be-iskopa lemachar pote'ach ve-no'el u-machziro limekomo
o
be-chalon she-al gabei petach*. Right, right. Okay, so we're going to
take a look. So that's going to be a problem. So the
גמרא Gemara. is going to say since the חכמים say since רבי
מאיר says, if you're standing in a כרמלית Karmelit. you can manipulate
it in the רשות היחיד, Reshut HaYachid. so that's going to seem
like רבי מאיר has reversed himself, which the גמרא Gemara will say,
and then the חכמים say, no, you can actually take it from
under your mat at the כרמלית Karmelit here and open up the
door. So the question is going to be, how can they say
that? You're taking from a כרמלית Karmelit to a רשות היחיד. Reshut
HaYachid You're actually physically taking it from a כרמלית Karmelit to a
רשות היחיד. Reshut HaYachid. So this ברייתא braita is going to be
a problem in both cases and the גמרא Gemara will deal with
it. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. מדקאמר אבני
חנויות, Mideka'amar avnei chanuyot,
since it's talking about the case of the stores, מכלל דבאיסקופא כרמלית
עסקינן. michlal d'be'iskopa Karmelit askinan.
So we're talking about this איסקופא iskopa here is a כרמלית. Karmelit.
Okay, we're no longer dealing with a רשות הרבים case, it's a
כרמלית. Karmelit, והאי מנעול היכי דמי, V'hai manul heichi dami, so what's
the case of the lock? אי דלית ביה ארבעה, Ei d'leit bei
arba'ah, if it's not four טפחים tfachim wide, מקום פטור הוא, makom
p'tur hu, then the whole thing is a מקום פטור Makom Patur.
and nobody should have a problem doing anything with it. ואי אית
ביה ארבעה, V'ei it bei arba'ah, if it is four טפחים, tfachim.
so this is exactly the question we were asking. הא לימא רבנן
אף בזמן שהמנעול למעלה מעשרה מביא מפתח מערב שבת ומניחו באיסקופא למחר
פותח ונועל בו ומחזירו לאיסקופא ולחלון שעל גבי הפתח? Ha leima Rabbanan
af bizman she'hamanul lemala mi'asara meivi mafteach me'erev Shabbat u'manicho b'iskopa l'machar
poteach v'noel bo u'machziro l'iskopa u'le'chalon she'al gabi hapetach? Okay,
so if basically long story short, if this contraption is four טפחים
tfachim. and it's four טפחים tfachim by four טפחים tfachim, and it's
ten טפחים high, it's a רשות היחיד. Reshut HaYachid. So how can
they say take your key from under the mat, which is a
כרמלית, Karmelit, and put it into the רשות היחיד? Reshut HaYachid, How
would you be allowed to do that? והא קמטלטל מכרמלית לרשות היחיד,
V'ha kamitaltel mi'Karmelit l'Reshut HaYachid, you're taking from a כרמלית Karmelit to
a רשות
היחיד. Reshut HaYachid. אמר אביי לעולם דלית ביה ארבעה, Amar Abaye le'olam
d'leit bei arba'ah, there's not four טפחים in this contraption. ויש בו
לחוק ולהשלימו לארבעה. V'yesh bo lachok u'lehashlimo l'arba'ah. You might remember this
גמרא Gemara. uses sometimes, you can in theory though it could be
carved out and made into four. So I was sort of drawing
it more like it was some type of external contraption. It sounds
more from the way it's described like it is
some type of an internal contraption that there's some type of a
thing here that goes into into the wall. And well now there's
still a picture here. It still looks external here, but anyway they've
got some...
yeah it looks like there is something dug out in the...
right, so there's something carved out and in a... yeah there's some
recess right in the wall. Okay, there's some niche in the wall
and it's carved into it. Okay, but it's not four by four,
it's three by three or something and it's got some contraption. So
you put the key in that's into the wall, that's a רשות
היחיד. Reshut HaYachid It looks the same, but anyway it's internal rather
than external and the idea is is whether in theory you could
carve it out to be four by four. Does that give it
a real or a pseudo רשות היחיד Reshut HaYachid, status? And that's
the debate. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Where is it? בהא פליגי, B'ha pligi, this is what they debate.
רבי מאיר סבר חוקקים להשלים, Rabbi Meir savar chokekim lehashlim, which we've
seen before. רבי מאיר says you would envision it as if if
it's less than four it was carved out, if it could be
carved out, maybe normally is carved out and therefore it's like it's
a רשות היחיד. Reshus Hayachid, רבנן סברי אין חוקקים להשלים, Rabbanan savri
ein chokekim lehashlim, you do not do that. Okay, so basically therefore
what is the explanation of this ברייתא? braita So basically רבי מאיר
says you're standing in the גינה, gina, you can manipulate the key.
Presumably here he's being lenient if you're standing in a כרמלית Karmelit.
and manipulating something in רשות היחיד. Reshus Hayachid And the רבנן Rabbanan
say you can even take it from the כרמלית, Karmelis. from the
איסקופא, iskopa, and do it in the lock for they don't treat
the lock as a רשות היחיד, Reshus Hayachid so it's all considered
to be essentially within a כרמלית. Karmelis, Now what is the last
line of this ברייתא that we said, that I ran over a
little bit? So if you go back, that's the issue of if
the lock is higher than ten טפחים. But what's the last point?
The last point is we just quoted it above: מביא מפתח מערב
שבת ומניחו באיסקופא למחר פותח ונועל בו. Meivi mafteach me'erev Shabbat u'manicho
b'iskopa l'machar poteach v'noel bo. Now what do you do after you've
opened it? ומחזירו לאיסקופא, U'machziro l'iskopa, put it back to the איסקופא.
iskopa. Well fine, if we decided now the איסקופא iskopa is a
כרמלית Karmelis and the lock is a כרמלית Karmelis because it doesn't
have four, you're going from כרמלית Karmelis to כרמלית. Karmelis, או לחלון
שעל גבי הפתח, O le'chalon she'al gabi hapetach,
or the window. Okay, now how big is the window? It says
if the window is four by four, it's אסור. asur. So what
do you do when you're done? You take it from your כרמלית,
Karmelis, you open this up, it's a כרמלית, Karmelis you either put
it back into a כרמלית or you can put it into a
window. Now what is the story of this window? Presumably it's higher
than ten טפחים. Okay, if the window is four טפחים by four
טפחים, then the window is a רשות היחיד. reshus ha-yachid. So you're
not allowed to go ahead and put it from here into the
window, because then you're going into a רשות היחיד Reshus Hayachid. and
you started here from a כרמלית. Okay, but when you do... so
what you do is you take it back here or you put
it in the window if the window is less than four. Because
if the window is four and a רשות היחיד, Reshus Hayachid. you
cannot go from the lock to the window. Now this lock... Actually,
if it's less than four by four, it's actually not a כרמלית.
Anything less than four by four is what? A מקום פטור. Makom
Patur. Okay, so you're in כרמלית, you're manipulating the lock according to
the rabbis which is a מקום פטור. Makom Patur. And then you
can go back as a כרמלית or to the window if the
window is also a מקום פטור. Makom Patur, But if the window
is four in a רשות היחיד, Reshus Hayachid. you cannot go to
the window. Okay, even though you're doing it via a מקום פטור,
Makom Patur, right? Because it goes כרמלית to פטור Patur is okay,
פטור Patur to רשות היחיד is okay, but since you started here,
you're doing it via מקום פטור, Makom Patur. it's no good. And
that's going to be the last point the גמרא Gemara makes. Let's
take a look at the גמרא. אמר
רבי ביבי בר אבא שמע מינה מהא מתניסא תלת. Amar Rabbi Bibi
bar Abba, shma mina me-ha matnisa telat. You can see from this
ברייתא three things. שמע מינה חוקקין להשלים Shma mina chokekim le-hashlim according
to רבי מאיר you dig it out to make it whole, which
means that according to רבי מאיר it's considered a רשות היחיד because
רבי מאיר has the problems that he has. Okay,
where were we? חוקקין להשלים. Chokekim le-hashlim. אמר... where were we? ושמע
מינה Ve-shma mina חדא דבי רבי מאיר משרי גינה, רבי מאיר reversed
himself from the case about the
gate of the garden because here you're in a כרמלית and you're
opening up this מפתח, this, you know, this lock. ושמע מינה
and we also learn מדרבנן midrabbanan from the rabbis איתא דרב דימי
isa de-Rav Dimi that we accept the position of רב דימי. Rav
Dimi. דכי אתא רב דימי אמר רבי יוחנן, De-ki asa Rav Dimi
amar Rabbi Yochanan, when רב דימי Rav Dimi came from ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael and said in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
מקום שאין בו ארבע על ארבע, Makom she-ein bo arba al arba,
if you have something that's not four by four, it's מקום פטור.
Makom Patur. מותר לבני רשות הרבים ולבני רשות היחיד לכתף עליו, Mutar
li-bnei reshus ha-rabim u-li-bnei reshus ha-yachid le-katef alav, it can be used
by either the people of רשות הרבים or רשות היחיד. ובלבד שלא
יחליפו, U-bilvad she-lo yachlifu,
but you can't use it as a stopping point to go from
one to the other. So this כרמלית, you're in a כרמלית, you
can put stuff in this lock, it's מקום פטור. Makom Patur If
something was started on this lock, you can put it into the
רשות היחיד. But you cannot take it from the כרמלית to the
מקום פטור Makom Patur and from there to the רשות היחיד. That's
what you're doing though, no? No, so that's why it said if
this is four by four you can't. If it's less than four
you can because it's a מקום פטור Makom Patur. to מקום פטור.
Makom Patur If it's four you can't because then it's מקום פטור
to a רשות היחיד. Okay, let's get started now on the next
משנה. נגר שיש בראשו גלוסטרא Nagar she-yesh be-rosho glustra and as Michael
said, I mean ממש mamash this is almost like the case of
the suspended door before, and like cases we had at the end
of מסכת שבת, Masechet Shabbat, we have now a bar, you got,
you know you have a lock, you know that's a bar that
goes between, you know your door and the wall, okay? And you're
going to use it to lock your door on שבת, but the
question is, if it's not, it hangs and it's suspended from the
door, how much is putting it into the holes
considered like בונה? boneh?
נגד הנגר ה... נגר התלוי. Neged ha-neger ha... neger ha-talui. Exactly.
So but you've got this thing now, it has on the head
of it a like bulb, it's got a bulbous head. So okay,
so
and therefore that makes it something that makes it even theoretically like
a כלי, kli, like a vessel, something you could use to, you
know, pound spices with or something like that. So רבי אליעזר אוסר,
Rabbi Eliezer oser, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it's forbidden and as
רש"י Rashi points out, unless it is קשור ותלוי, kashur ve-talui, which
is like what we have before, again, suspended, you know, tied and
suspended, that makes it part of the door and you're not being
בונה. boneh. רבי יוסי מתיר. Rabbi Yose matir. Now רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose says no, it's like you took, let's say you took a
spoon, okay, and you stuck it in, you know, to like these
holes in the door or whatever, you know, to hold the thing
there. So that's not a real בונה, boneh, you're not leaving it
there permanently, clearly it's an ad-hoc fix. Okay, so the question is,
as we know from the discussion before about door and another discussion
in מסכת שבת, Masechet Shabbat, you need these things that are, you
know, stopping up holes and filling up walls, you know, filling up
windows, you need them to be tied to the wall and suspended.
But how about if it's clearly a completely ad-hoc temporary fix and
nobody considers it part of the structure? Can you use this thing
that's used for pounding spices and use it to, you know, to
stick into these holes temporarily without it being tied and suspended? So
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says no and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says
yes. אמר רבי אליעזר, Amar Rabbi Eliezer, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said
מעשה בכנסת שבטבריה, maaseh bi-chneset she-be-Tverya, a story in the synagogue in
Tiberias, which I think also is interesting about some of these last
cases is that you have, you know, bringing from real cases, you
know, it's not, there's a number of these things now that they're
bringing evidence from actual cases. So there was a story in the
synagogue in Tiberias שהיו נוהגים בו היתר she-hayu noghim bo heter that
they used to say that that was okay to do as long
as it's got this bulbous head, עד שבא רבן גמליאל וזקנים ואסרו
להם ad she-ba Rabban Gamliel ve-zkeinim ve-asru la-hem until רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel and the elders came and said that it was forbidden
and they said "Whoa, what are you doing? It's אסור." asur רבי
יוסי אומר איסור נהגו בו, Rabbi Yose omer, issur nahagu bo, you
got it reversed. They used to say it was אסור ובא רבן
גמליאל וזקנים והתירו להם u-va Rabban Gamliel ve-zkeinim ve-hisiru la-hem and רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and the elders came and said it was מותר.
mutar. Okay,
so let's take a look at the very short גמרא on this
and then I'll read you a brief תוספות Tosafot on that. So
the גמרא says like this, בנטל באגדו כולי עלמא לא פליגי bi-nittol
be-agdo kulei alma lo pligi
if it is something that can be, that the, you know, this
bar can be lifted up by the rope it's attached to, then
of course it's okay, then it's like it's part of the
door. כי פליגי בשאינו... ki pligi be-she-eino... or the rope
will break. מר סבר כיון דאיכא בראשה גלוסטרא תורת כלי עליה. Mar
savar keivan deika berosha glustra torat kli aleiha. One holds since it's
got this this pounding thing it's like a vessel and it's not
really that you're you're adding something to the door you're not really
doing any serious construction. It's clearly an ad hoc fix. ומר סבר
כיון דלא ניטל באגדו לא. Umar savar keivan dela nital beagdo lo.
And the other says I'm sorry if it's not seriously tied to
the wall and you can't pick it up by the rope it's
not considered to be a part of the contraption so and and
therefore it is like you are adding to the wall and it
and to the structure and it's a problem. I just want to
read you a short תוספות. Tosafot. רבי יוסי אומר איסור נוהג בו
והתירו להם. Rabbi Yossi omer isur noheig bo vehitiru lahem. תוספות Tosafot
says ואם תאמר והאמרינן בנדרים פרק ואלו נדרים פרק מקום שנהגו דברים
המותרים וכן נהגו בהן איסור אי אתה
רשאי להתיר בפניהם. Veim tomar vehaamrinan binedarim perek veeilu nedarim perek makom
shenahagu devarim hamutarim vechein nahagu bahen isur i atah rashai lehatir bifneihem.
How could you come and say it's מותר? mutar? Don't we say
that if people are treating something as איסור isur you can't go
ahead and tell them it's מותר? mutar? ויש לומר דהיינו כשיודעים שמותר
ומחמירים על עצמן. Veyeish lomar dehaynu keshoyodim shemutar umachmirim al atzman.
That's if they have a חומרא chumra and they know it's a
חומרא, chumra, then you can't come ahead and say oh you have
to do differently. We know we're doing a חומרא, chumra, it doesn't
matter that the הלכה halacha is that it's מותר. mutar. שלא ירגילו
בני אדם להקל ויבואו להתיר איסור. Shelo yargilu bnei adam lehakeil veyavo'u
lehatir isur. And there you shouldn't go ahead because then they if
they experience this as something that's forbidden and you're going to tell
them it's מותר, mutar, so you know that that could lead to
terrible things, they'll they'll translate that into other things that they think
are forbidden. אבל אם מחמירים מחמת טעות, Aval im machmirim machamat taut,
but if they're making a mistake, מותר להתיר בפניהם. mutar lehatir bifneihem.
You can correct error. Okay, so you can't go ahead and tell
them it's מותר mutar if it's a חומרא, chumra, okay, because then
it's not an error, I mean you might not like the חומרא,
chumra, but it's there but you but you don't have to buy
in to ignorance, okay? And if they're actually making a mistake and
they're ignorant of something, then you're allowed to מתיר. matir. And it's
like I think I mentioned this before, a very interesting תשובה tshuva
of רב משה Rav Moshe about מראית עין. marit ayin. רב משה
Rav Moshe says, you know, מראית עין marit ayin is
when people know the הלכה halacha but they might misunderstand the facts,
like they might think that this is, you know, real cheese when
it's really soy cheese. And that's when you have to be worried
about what people are going to think. But he says if people
have a mistake about the הלכה, halacha, okay, you don't have to
buy into their ignorance. Like let's say for example I have a
student said to me like, let's say you left something in your
car on שבת, okay, and the interior light is off. Okay, you
can open up this door
on שבת. Well yeah, anyway so
רב משה Rav Moshe says you don't have to buy into people's
ignorance, actually you shouldn't. Why should you right try to tailor to
people's ignorance? So it's actually an interesting point, this idea you're actually
allowed to correct people and maybe should correct people if they're making
a mistake. Okay, you don't buy into the error or to the
ignorance of of other people, you work to correct it. And we
will end that.